<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gloucester's triumph at the solemn proclamation of King Charles the Second; on Tuesday the 15th. day of May 1660.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G884B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202225</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825161</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825161</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29536</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42866)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29536)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 1778:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gloucester's triumph at the solemn proclamation of King Charles the Second; on Tuesday the 15th. day of May 1660.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.C. for H. Fletcher, at the three gilt Cups in S. Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term>Gloucester (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29536:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>GLO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CESTER'S</hi> TRIUMPH AT THE Solemn PROCLAMATION OF King Charles the Second; On Tueſday the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. day of <hi>May</hi> 1660.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>H. Fletcher,</hi> at the three gilt Cups in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Churchyard. 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29536:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29536:2"/>
            <head>Glouceſters triumph, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe ſolemnity uſed by the City of <hi>Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> on Tueſday laſt, at the Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Majeſty King <hi>CHARLES</hi> the ſecond, was accompanyed with ſuch demonſtration of real affection to the buſineſs they went about, and of undoubted loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to his Majeſty, and of truly glad hearts at the revolution of affairs into that hopeful poſture where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in now they ſtand, that I could not but take the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, that is now offered, to acquaint you with a true Narrative thereof. The manner, thus: In ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of ſuch an opportunity, the Mayor of the City, Colonel <hi>Toby Jordan,</hi> gave Orders for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting of a Scaffold before the Market-place; which could not be finiſhed before the Proclamation came down: but being come, on <hi>Saturday</hi> laſt he ſent for the Lieutenants, Enſignes, and Serjeants of his own Regiment, and thoſe alſo of Colonel <hi>Twiſleton's</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment now in the City, together with the Drums of both Regiments, to give publick notice in every ſtreet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29536:3"/>at market-time by beat of Drum, that the Tueſday following was appointed to proclaim the King: and to the ſame purpoſe, ſome of the Militia-troops of the County were alſo invited to attend the ſolemnity on the day appointed. By that time the day came, the Scaffold was finiſhed, being very large, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as it were) into two rooms; the firſt being low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then theſe old by three aſcents; and both accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated with Utenſils ſuitable, for the more ſtately ſitting of each man according to his quality; and the whole Scaffold (both above and below) was round about hung with yellow cloath, as being the colour of the Militia-Regiment for the City and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>County, commanded by Mr. Mayor. The place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Mayors chair, was hung with Arras, adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his Majeſties Atchievement-royal. Divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preparations there were. For the common ſort, the water was turned out of the three publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits of the City, and wine was placed in the ciſterns. Beſides which, there were Runlets of wine, and cakes provided for each Company and Troop: both the City, and ſome of the Gentry, contributed their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance largely this way.</p>
            <p>The noiſt of this publick notice of the day, and the preparations which were made, drew a mighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of people from all parts on the day appointed, men, women and children; Many of the Gentry, Miniſtry, and people of all qualities, to the number of ſcarce ſo few as ten thouſand; ſo that I never ſaw the City ſo crowded in all my life; all, both of the City and County, unanimouſly teſtifying then joy for the appearance of this long-looked-for day. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29536:3"/>were there more ſignificant Expreſſions of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hearts appearing in the very faces and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of all ſorts of perſons, then on that occaſion.</p>
            <p>Well, the day being come, and it being Lecture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and the ſtreets ſtrowed with green; the market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>places adorned with Garlands, and the Kings boord, beſides ſuch ornaments, cloathed round about with white cloath, the Mayor appointed all the Maſters and Wardens of the ſeveral Guilds and Fraternities, with their Streamers and Trophies belonging to each Company, to wait upon him, and the Aldermen and Common-Council, (himſelf and the Aldermen, She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs and Sheriffs Peers in Scarlet, and all the reſt in their ſeveral Garbs, befitting their eſtate and degree) to the Cathedral Church, with trumpets ſounding, and the ſeveral Conſtables with the ſtaves of their office walking before, each arrayed with white ſcarffs tyed with purple and green: whither when they were come, Mr. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Cambden,</hi> (whoſe Lecture-turn it was) preached an excellent and ſeaſonable Sermon on <hi>Luke</hi> 7.21, 22. <hi>When the ſtrong man armed keepeth his palace, his goods are in peace: but when a ſtronger then he ſhall come upon him, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him, he taketh from him all his armour wherein he truſted, and divideth his ſpoile.</hi> Wherein he ſhewed the proper drift of the Text, (as his Lecture-work) in the beginning, and cloſed all with a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uitable pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel in the cloſe, (pro<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er to the ſol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mnity of that day) in all expreſſing great affections to the occaſion of that day<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ap<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y meeting. Sermon being ended, the Mayor in the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> Equipage as before, re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed home; and a while after, the Sheriffs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with their <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaves,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29536:4"/>and the Aldermen, and others of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Council fetch'd Mr. Mayor from his own houſe to the <hi>Tolſey:</hi> by which time, nine Companies of foot were marched from the place of their randezvouz in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the City, and drawn up to the moſt convenient places for the giving their Martial <hi>Euges</hi> to this work. And a little after, three Troops of Horſe drawn up with ſuch convenience as the ſtraightneſs of the place could afford. All things being thus in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Maior in the like equipage as before, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched from the <hi>Tolſey</hi> to the Scaffold (which beſides the Ornaments before mentioned, was now ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſix Garlands after the form of Crowns, born up with long white ſtaves in the hands of ſix Virgins of the Gentry, in ſix ſeveral places) whither and where he was attended by many of the Gentry of the County, the Aldermen and Common Council of the City, in their reſpective Robes; a very conſiderable number of grave Divines, the City Miniſters being in their Gowns. All being ſeated or placed as the Room would give leave, the Trumpets ſounded again and again; and at length, <hi>O yes,</hi> being made by Mr. Sheriff <hi>Scudamore</hi> ſeveral times, Mr. Sheriff <hi>Snell</hi> read the Proclamation, and the <hi>Senior</hi> Sheriff recited it after him with a diſtinct and audible voice. Which being done, Mr. Maior ſtanding up upon his Chair, drew his Martial Sword in the fight of all the people, for a token of his readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to uſe it in the defence of his Majeſty, and for a ſignal to all the reſt of the Officers and Souldiers to do the like in that nick of time, and to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies in ſight to give fire. And they were no whit
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29536:4"/>behind in their duty; for inſtantly this ſignal was followed with the like by all in Armes, loud accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of all ſorts, Crying out, <hi>God ſave King CHARLES the ſecond, Long live King CHARLES;</hi> and exact Volleys of ſhot from the ſeveral Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Troops in ſuch order as was before deviſed, and theſe reiterated: ſo that we were in the midſt of fire and ſmoak for a long ſeaſon (but without danger, and with ſuch rejoycings of all ſorts as is unſpeakable.) When things grew ſomwhat calm, another <hi>O yes</hi> was made, and the Declaration of the Honorable Houſe of Commons was read, which was ſeconded with the like acclamations to his Majeſties wellfare, and many Volleys of ſhot. Which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued all the while they were on the Scaffold, and there they ſtayed no ſmall time: For unto them were brought Wine and Cakes, where they rejoyced publickly, whilſt much was diſtributed to Gentry and ſtrangers in houſes, while the Conduits ran Claret, and the Souldiers in their ſeveral Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Troops had their ſhares brought to them. This done, ſeveral Companies and Troops marched by, giving their ſeveral volleys; and the Aſſembly was diſmiſt. By this time the day was far ſpent, the Bells every where ringing, and Bonfires every where flaming; in one of which, the States Armes vaniſhed into ſmoak. All the Solemnity was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with Fire-works, Rockets of many ſorts, fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and running; an excellent peal of Reporters; and at laſt the Wheel went round. The Wheel of State (God be thanked) is ſo, and come into its right po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. It will be endleſs to tell you the rejoycings we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29536:5"/>here have. You could not obſerve a ſowre look, or a dejected countenance that day; and yet in all my obſervation (and it is the obſervation of many more, that) there were few or none overtaken with drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs that day in all that great multitude: which was one addition to the joy of them, who deſire to rejoyce in temporal mercies, ſo as in the Lord. And I could wiſh, all would learn to honour God and the King with the holineſs of their lives and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations; and that all places were at unity within themſelves, and united in their reſolutions of Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as this little City and populous County is.</p>
            <p>The good affection your Honour bears to this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, made me willing to give your Honour this rude account of what hath paſſed among us in that days tranſaction. The Lord preſerve his Majeſty long to Reign over us, and return him to his Parliament and People with honour, and direct the Counſels of both the Honourable Houſes of Parliament, that there may be peace and truth in our days. So prays</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Glouceſter, <date>May 16. 1660.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your humble Orator.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
